Williams Obstetrics.
Chapter 28: Singleton Breech Delivery.
Classification Diagnosis Delivery Route Labor And Delivery Partial Breech Extraction Total Breech Extraction External Cephalic Version References Classification Near term, the typical fetus spontaneously assumes a cephalic presentation.
However, if the fetal buttocks or legs enter the pelvis before the head, the presentation is breech.
At term, breech presentation persists in 2 to 5 percent of singleton deliveries (Bin, 2016; Cammu, 2014; Toijonen, 2019).
Breech delivery of a second twin is discussed in Chapter 48 (p. 856).
The categories of frank, complete, and incomplete breech presentations differ in their varying relations between the lower extremities and buttocks.
With a frank breech, lower extremities are flexed at the hips and extended at the knees, and thus the feet lie close to the head .
With a complete breech, both hips are flexed, and one or both knees are also flexed (Fig. 28- 2).
With an incomplete breech, one or both hips are extended.
As a result, one or both feet or knees lie below the breech, and thus a foot or knee is lowermost in the birth canal.
A footling breech is an incomplete breech with one or both feet below the breech.
Figure 28-1.
Frank breech presentation.
Figure 28-2.
Complete breech presentation.
Of singleton term breech fetuses, the neck may be extremely hyperextended in perhaps 5 percent, and the term stargazing fetus is used .
With transverse lie and similar hyperextension of the fetal neck, the term flying fetus is applied.
With these, fetal or uterine anomalies may be more prevalent and are sought if not previously identified (Phelan, 1983; Shipp, 2000).
With hyperextension, vaginal delivery can injure the cervical spinal cord.
Thus, if identified at term, cesarean delivery is indicated .
However, cases of spinal cord injury have been reported following uneventful cesarean delivery of breech fetuses.
Here, the flexion itself may be implicated (Hernandez-Marti, 1984; Weinstein, 1983).
Diagnosis.
# Risk Factors.
Understanding the clinical settings that predispose to breech presentation can aid early recognition.
This fetal lie is more common remote from term, as earlier in pregnancy each fetal pole has similar bulk .
Multifetal gestation is another .
With singletons, other factors include extremes of amnionic fluid volume, fetal anomalies, structural uterine abnormalities, placenta previa, nulliparity, increased maternal age, female fetal gender, prior breech delivery, and size that is small for gestational age (Bin, 2016; Cammu, 2014; Noli, 2019; Roberts, 1999).
One study found that following one breech delivery, the recurrence rate for a second breech presentation was 10 percent, and for a subsequent third breech it was 28 percent .
# Examination.
Leopold maneuvers to ascertain fetal presentation are discussed in Chapter 22 (p. 419).
With the first maneuver, the hard, round fetal head occupies the fundus.
The second maneuver identifies the hard, broad back to be on one side of the abdomen and the knobby small parts on the other.
With the third maneuver, if not engaged, the softer breech is movable above the pelvic inlet.
After engagement, the fourth maneuver shows the breech to be beneath the symphysis.
The accuracy of this palpation varies (Lydon-Rochelle, 1993; Nassar, 2006).
Thus, with unclear presentation, sonographic examination is indicated.
During cervical examination with a frank breech, no feet are appreciated, but the fetal ischial tuberosities, sacrum, and anus are usually palpable.
After further fetal descent, the external genitalia also may be distinguished.
When labor is prolonged, the fetal buttocks may become markedly swollen, rendering digital differentiation of a face and breech difficult.
In some cases, the anus may be mistaken for the mouth and the ischial tuberosities for the malar eminences.
With careful examination, however, the finger encounters muscular resistance with the anus, whereas the bony, less yielding jaws and palate are felt through the mouth.
The finger, upon removal from the anus, may be
stained with meconium.
The mouth and malar eminences form a triangular shape, whereas the ischial tuberosities and anus lie in a straight line.
With a complete breech, the feet may be felt alongside the buttocks.
In footling presentations, one or both feet are inferior to the buttocks.
The fetal sacrum is palpated to establish position.
As with cephalic presentations, fetal position is designated to reflect the relations of the fetal sacrum to the maternal pelvis.
Thus, with left sacrum anterior (LSA), the fetus’s back is up and its sacrum occupies the left upper (ventral) quadrant of the mother’s pelvis.
Other positions are right sacrum anterior (RSA), right or left sacrum posterior (RSP or LSP), and right or left sacrum transverse (RST or LST).
Delivery Route.
Multiple factors aid determination of the best delivery route.
These include maternal parity and pelvic dimensions; coexistent pregnancy complications; provider experience; patient preference; hospital capabilities; and fetal size, anatomy, and gestational age .
Table 28-1.
Factors Favoring Cesarean Delivery of the Breech Fetus Compared with their term counterparts, preterm breech fetuses have distinct complications related to their small size and immaturity.
Accordingly, a separate discussion of term and preterm breech fetuses is presented.
# Term Breech Fetus.
Current obstetrical thinking regarding vaginal delivery of the term breech fetus was tremendously influenced by results of the Term Breech Trial .
This trial included 1041 women randomly assigned to planned cesarean and 1042 to planned vaginal delivery.
These comparator groups reflect actual risks, and the planned vaginal delivery group included those who required intrapartum cesarean delivery.
In the planned vaginal delivery group, 57 percent were actually delivered vaginally.
Planned cesarean delivery was associated with a lower risk of perinatal mortality compared with planned vaginal delivery—3 per 1000 versus 13 per 1000.
Cesarean delivery was also associated with a lower risk of “serious” neonatal morbidity—1.4 versus 3.8 percent.
Short-term maternal morbidity was similar between groups.
Critics of the Term Breech Trial emphasize that fewer than 10 percent of candidates underwent radiological assessment of pelvic capacity.
In addition, most of the outcomes included in the “serious” neonatal morbidity composite did not actually portend long-term infant disability .
Since that trial, however, additional data favoring cesarean delivery has come from the World Health Organization .
In more than 100,000 deliveries from nine participating Asian countries, planned cesarean delivery offered improved perinatal outcomes for the term breech fetus compared with planned vaginal delivery.
Other studies also have found lowered neonatal morbidity and mortality rates with cesarean delivery (Lyons, 2015; Rietberg, 2005; Vistad, 2015).
From one metaanalysis, the calculated absolute risk of perinatal mortality was 0.3 percent, and risk of fetal birth trauma or neurological morbidity was 0.7 percent .
In contrast, other studies support vaginal delivery as a suitable option at term .
The Presentation et Mode d’Accouchement (PREMODA) study—which translates as presentation and mode of delivery —showed no differences in corrected neonatal mortality rates and neonatal outcomes according to delivery mode .
Severe acute maternal morbidity scores were similar .
This French prospective observational study involved more than 8000 women with term breech singletons.
Strict criteria were used to select 2526 of these for planned vaginal delivery, and 71 percent of that group were delivered vaginally.
Data from the Lille Breech Study Group in France also showed no excessive morbidity in term breech singletons delivered vaginally provided that strict fetal biometric and maternal pelvimetry parameters were applied .
Other smaller studies support these findings as long as guidelines are part of the selection process (Alarab, 2004; Giuliani, 2002; Toivonen, 2012).
Long-term evidence supporting vaginal breech
delivery comes from Eide and associates (2005).
These investigators analyzed intelligence testing scores of more than 8000 men delivered breech, and delivery route did not affect later intellectual performance.
Moreover, a 2-year follow-up from the Term Breech trial showed similar risks for death and for neurodevelopmental delay between delivery groups .
Other studies support these findings (Bin, 2017; Macharey, 2018).
Despite evidence for this debate, at least in the United States, rates of planned vaginal delivery attempts continue to decline .
Thus, as predicted, the number of skilled providers able to safely select and vaginally deliver breech fetuses steadily dwindles .
Moreover, obvious medicolegal concerns make physician training in such deliveries difficult.
In response, some institutions have developed birth simulators to improve resident competence in vaginal breech delivery (Deering, 2006; Maslovitz, 2007).
In selecting suitable term breech vaginal delivery candidates, factors outlined in Table 28-1 are weighed.
Of these, various national organizations recommend that the estimated term fetal weight lies between >2500 to 2800 g and <3800 to 4000 g (American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists, 2018b; Impey, 2017b; Kotaska, 2019).
Fetal-growth restriction and oligohydramnios are other contraindications, because of their inherent association with poor neonatal outcome (Chaps.
14 and 47, pp. 260 and 831).
Data support this concern for the term breech fetus (Hinnenberg, 2019; Macharey, 2017a).
Of uterine factors, prior hysterotomy carries an inherent risk for rupture in labor.
The PREMODA, Term Breech Trial, and other studies allowed a trial of labor after cesarean for vaginal breech delivery, but in each, these constituted a small percentage of participants.
Other studies have considered prior cesarean as a contraindication.
Very limited data suggest a possible link with adverse perinatal outcome (Azria, 2012; Macharey, 2017a).
Moreover, a prior cesarean delivery performed for arrested labor may suggest a relatively contracted pelvis and a greater labor risk.
In contrast, parity and prior vaginal birth are positive factors and likely reflect sufficient pelvic capacity.
Last, those with spontaneous labor and normal labor curves have higher successful vaginal birth rates.
# Preterm Breech Fetus.
In contrast to the term breech fetus, no randomized trials guide delivery selection for the preterm breech fetus.
Comparison of the available observational studies is often hampered by their combining, splitting, or overlapping of gestational age groups.
Other study biases include differing gestational age thresholds for planned neonatal resuscitation, assigning mortality causation to delivery rather than immaturity, and tendency to favor vaginal delivery for fetuses with a poor prognosis.
In addition, the effects of precipitous vaginal delivery and associated incomplete antenatal prophylaxis with corticosteroids and antibiotics is difficult to evaluate.
Despite these limitations, for preterm breech fetuses as whole, data support that planned cesarean delivery confers a survival advantage compared with planned vaginal delivery.
Reddy and associates (2012) reported data from deliveries between 24 and 32 weeks’ gestation.
For breech fetuses within these gestational ages, attempting vaginal delivery yielded a low success rate, and this group was associated with higher neonatal mortality rates compared with planned cesarean delivery.
From a metaanalysis incorporating data from more than 3500 parturients, similar mortality associations were reported .
In contrast, in their smaller cohort with gestational ages of 26 to 34 weeks, Lorthe and coworkers (2019) found similar rates of survival or of survival at discharge without severe morbidity.
For less mature subgroups—23 to 28 weeks—the data are more conflicting as to whether survival rates are improved with planned cesarean delivery (Bergenhenegouwen, 2015; Grabovac, 2018; Kayem, 2015; Thomas, 2016; Tucker Edmonds, 2015).
In the balance, cesarean delivery is
proposed to avoid fetal injury from vaginal birth that may include anoxia, trauma, and head entrapment.
This is measured against maternal morbidity from a classical uterine incision, which is often needed in this early preterm group due to a poorly developed lower uterine segment.
This incision typically poses a risk of greater blood loss, higher infection rate, and increased risk of uterine rupture in future pregnancies (Patterson, 2002; Reddy, 2015; Sciscione, 2008).
The high-level skills needed for safe vaginal delivery of the very preterm fetus and the ultimate prognosis of the neonate are other directing factors.
For periviable fetuses, defined by them as 20 to 256/7 weeks, a consensus workshop of perinatal organizations concluded that “available data do not consistently support routine cesarean delivery to improve perinatal mortality or neurological outcomes for early preterm infants” .
A subsequent joint statement by the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists and the Society for Maternal-Fetal Medicine (2017) suggested consideration for cesarean delivery for periviable fetuses beginning at 230/7 weeks, with a recommendation for cesarean delivery at 250/7 weeks.
For more mature preterm breech fetuses, that is, between 32 and 37 weeks, again limited data guide delivery route selection.
Bergenhenegouwen and coworkers (2015) studied more than 6800 breech deliveries in a subgroup between 32 and 37 weeks.
With planned cesarean delivery or planned vaginal birth, they found similar perinatal mortality and morbidity rates.
All these findings shape practice.
Thus, individualized decision-making is needed for the preterm breech fetus for whom resuscitation is planned.
Provider skill, gestational age, parity, labor curve, and facility capability weigh heavily in this process.
For the fetus in which resuscitation is not planned, vaginal delivery is likely preferable.
# Delivery Complications.
Compared with cephalic-presenting fetuses, higher rates of maternal and perinatal morbidity can be anticipated with breech presentations.
For the mother, with either cesarean or vaginal delivery, genital tract laceration can be problematic.
With cesarean delivery, added stretching of the lower uterine segment by forceps or by a poorly molded fetal head can extend hysterotomy incisions.
With vaginal delivery, especially with a thinned lower uterine segment, delivery of the aftercoming head through an incompletely dilated cervix or application of forceps may cause vaginal wall or cervical lacerations, and even uterine rupture.
Manipulations may also extend an episiotomy, create deep perineal tears, require cervical incision, and raise infection risks.
If needed in select cases, inhalant anesthesia sufficient to induce appreciable uterine relaxation during vaginal delivery may cause uterine atony and postpartum hemorrhage.
Maternal death is rare, but rates appear higher in those with planned cesarean delivery for breech presentation—a case-fatality rate of 0.47 maternal deaths per 1000 births .
Other general short-term and long-term risks of cesarean delivery are listed in Chapter 30 (p. 548).
For the fetus, prematurity and its complications are frequently comorbid with breech presentation.
Rates of congenital anomalies also are greater .
Compared with cephalic presentation, umbilical cord prolapse is more frequent with breech fetuses and with breech vaginal delivery (Behbehani, 2016; Critchlow, 1994).
Collea (1980) reported that the incidence of prolapse approximated 0.5 percent with frank breech presentation, 5 percent with complete breech, and up to 15 percent with footling presentation.
Rare fetal morbidity includes humeral or clavicular fracture, brachial plexus injury, and sternocleidomastoid muscle trauma (Chap. 33, p. 609.
These may occur with either route but more frequently complicate vaginal birth.
However, cesarean birth does not appear to afford greater protection against femur or skull fractures (Ekéus, 2019; Goffinet, 2006; Hannah, 2000).
Rarely, traction may separate scapular, humeral, or femoral
epiphyses .
The spinal cord may be injured or vertebrae fractured, especially if great force is employed .
Last, genitals may be injured with breech delivery .
Some perinatal outcomes are inherent to the breech position rather than delivery.
For example, development of hip dysplasia is more common in breech compared with cephalic presentation and is unaffected by delivery mode (de Hundt, 2012; Hinderaker, 1994).
# Imaging.
As noted, limited sonographic evaluation near term is reasonable to confirm presentation.
Transabdominal sonography of the lower uterine segment in the sagittal plane shows the presenting fetal part.
Prior to this and as part of prenatal care, sonographic fetal survey will have been performed in most cases.
If not, gross fetal abnormalities, such as hydrocephaly or anencephaly, can be rapidly ascertained with sonography.
This will identify many fetuses not suitable for vaginal delivery.
It will also help to ensure that a cesarean delivery is not performed under emergency conditions for an anomalous fetus with no chance of survival.
In many fetuses—especially those that are preterm or growth restricted— the breech is smaller than the aftercoming head.
Moreover, unlike cephalic presentations, the head of a breech-presenting fetus does not undergo appreciable molding during labor.
Thus, if vaginal delivery is considered, fetal size, breech type, and degree of neck flexion are evaluated (Fontenot, 1997; Rojansky, 1994).
If needed, simple two-view radiography of the maternal abdomen also can define fetal head inclination.
Sonographic identification of a nuchal arm or nuchal cord loops may warrant cesarean delivery to avoid neonatal harm .
The accuracy of fetal weight estimation by sonography is not altered by breech presentation .
For planned vaginal delivery at term, thresholds in Table 28-1 guide care.
Moreover, a biparietal diameter (BPD) >90 to 100 mm is often considered exclusionary for vaginal delivery (Giuliani, 2002; Roman, 2008).
Pelvimetry In addition to these requisite fetal parameters, some institutional protocols recommend pelvimetry to assess the maternal bony pelvis prior to planned vaginal term breech birth.
Others, including our practice at Parkland Hospital, instead monitor the steady progression of fetal descent and cervical dilation to reflect adequate pelvic capacity.
For pelvimetry, one-view computed tomography (CT), magnetic resonance (MR) imaging, or plain film radiography is suitable.
Comparative data among these modalities for pelvimetry are lacking, but CT is favored due to its accuracy, low radiation dose, and widespread availability .
Although variable, some suggest specific measurements to permit a planned vaginal delivery: inlet anteroposterior diameter ≥10.5 cm; inlet transverse diameter ≥12.0 cm; and midpelvic interspinous distance ≥10.0 cm (Azria, 2012; Vendittelli, 2006).
Some have recommended maternal-fetal biometry correlation.
Appropriate values include: the sum of the inlet obstetrical conjugate minus the fetal BPD is ≥15 mm; the inlet transverse diameter minus the BPD is ≥25 mm; and the midpelvis interspinous distance minus the BPD is ≥0 mm .
From small studies of MR imaging, vaginal delivery success rates approximating 75 percent were noted if the interspinous distance was >11 cm and true obstetrical conjugate was >12 cm (Hoffmann, 2016; Klemt, 2019).
Labor And Delivery.
# Labor Management.
On arrival to the labor unit, surveillance of fetal heart rate and uterine contractions begins, and immediate recruitment of necessary staff includes: (1) a provider skilled in the art of breech extraction, (2) an associate to assist with the delivery, (3) anesthesia personnel who can ensure adequate analgesia or anesthesia when needed, and (4) an individual trained in newborn resuscitation.
For the mother, intravenous access is obtained.
This allows, if required, emergency induction of anesthesia or maternal resuscitation following hemorrhage from lacerations or from uterine atony.
Assessing cervical dilation, membranes status, and presenting part
station is essential for management.
If labor is too far advanced, pelvimetry may be unsafe if fetal expulsion in the radiology department is a possibility.
This alone, however, should not force the decision for cesarean delivery.
Commonly, stepwise labor progression itself is a good indicator of pelvic adequacy .
Sonographic assessment, described earlier, is completed.
Ultimately, the choice of abdominal or vaginal delivery is guided by factors listed in Table 28-1.
During labor, one-on-one nursing is ideal because of increased cord prolapse risks, and physicians must be readily available for such emergencies.
Guidelines for monitoring the high-risk fetus are applied .
For first-stage labor, most clinicians prefer continuous electronic monitoring.
At minimum, the fetal heart rate is recorded every 15 minutes.
A scalp electrode can be safely affixed to the buttock, but genitalia are avoided.
When membranes rupture, either spontaneously or artificially, the cord prolapse risk rises appreciably.
A small or preterm fetus or a non-frank breech presentation raises this risk.
Therefore, vaginal examination is performed immediately following rupture, and special attention is directed to the fetal heart rate for the first 5 to 10 minutes thereafter.
Continuous epidural analgesia is advocated by some.
This may increase the need for labor augmentation and prolong second-stage labor (Chadha, 1992; Confino, 1985).
These potential disadvantages are weighed against the advantages of better pain relief and increased pelvic relaxation should extensive fetal manipulation be required.
Analgesia must be sufficient for episiotomy, for breech extraction, and for Piper forceps application.
Nitrous oxide plus oxygen inhalation provides further relief from pain.
If general anesthesia is required, it must be induced quickly.
Normal second-stage labor should show progressive fetal descent.
An initial passive second stage allows the breech to advance to the perineum and is recommended.
In the PREMODA study, this stage lasted 60 min for only 20 percent .
For this passive phase, some recommend cesarean if the breech is not visible after 1½ to 2 hours (Impey, 2017b; Kotaska, 2019).
Once the breech is visible, active pushing is encouraged.
A hands-off approach in which hands are poised merely to support delivering parts is preferred to allow spontaneous delivery.
In the PREMODA study, this active phase was <30 min for 95 percent of those with successful vaginal births .
In their subanalysis of adverse neonatal outcome factors, an active second stage >20 min increased the risk .
In the Term Breech Trial, the lowest risk for maternal and neonatal adverse outcomes was seen in the group with active second stages lasting <30 min (Su, 2003, 2007).
In one small observational study, fetal adverse risks rose if this phase was >40 minutes .
Canadian guidelines recommend cesarean if completed or imminent delivery is not accomplished after 60 min of pushing .
# Labor Induction or Augmentation.
Induction or augmentation of labor is controversial for term breech pregnancies.
Here again, data are limited and mostly retrospective.
With labor induction, Burgos and coworkers (2017) reported equivalent vaginal delivery rates compared with spontaneous labor.
With induction, however, they reported higher rates of neonatal intensive care unit (NICU) admission.
But, Marzouk and associates (2011) found perinatal outcomes and cesarean delivery rates not to differ.
Last, others described greater cesarean delivery rates with induction but similar neonatal outcomes .
In a metaanalysis of studies, the NICU admission rate was 3 percent with labor induction and was double that of those delivered from spontaneous labor.
The cesarean delivery rate with induction was higher and was 33 percent .
Compared with cephalic presentations, breech labor in general proceeds more slowly, but steady cervical progress is a positive indicator of adequate pelvic capacity .
Thus, some protocols avoid augmentation for the
breech-presenting fetus, whereas others recommend it only for hypotonic contractions (Alarab, 2004; Kotaska, 2019).
In women with a viable fetus, at Parkland Hospital, we use amniotomy to promote contractions but prefer cesarean delivery instead of pharmacological labor induction or augmentation.
# Vaginal Delivery Methods.
Vaginal breech delivery is accomplished by one of three methods.
With spontaneous breech delivery, the fetus is expelled entirely without any traction or manipulation other than support of the newborn.
With partial breech extraction, the fetus is delivered spontaneously as far as the umbilicus, but the remainder of the body is delivered by provider traction and assisted maneuvers, with or without maternal expulsive efforts.
With total breech extraction, the entire fetal body is extracted by the provider.
# Spontaneous Breech Delivery.
Similar to vertex delivery, spontaneous expulsion of a breech fetus entails sequential cardinal movements .
First, engagement and descent of the breech usually take place with the bitrochanteric diameter in one of the oblique pelvic diameters.
The anterior hip usually descends more rapidly than the posterior hip, and when the resistance of the pelvic floor is met, internal rotation of 45 degrees usually follows, bringing the anterior hip toward the pubic arch and allowing the bitrochanteric diameter to occupy the anteroposterior diameter of the pelvic outlet.
After rotation, descent continues until the perineum is distended by the advancing breech, and the anterior hip appears at the vulva.
By lateral flexion of the fetal body, the posterior hip then is forced over the perineum, which retracts over the fetal buttocks, thus allowing the fetus to straighten out when the anterior hip is born.
The legs and feet follow the breech and may be born spontaneously or require aid.
After the birth of the breech, there is slight external rotation, with the back turning anteriorly as the shoulders are brought into relation with one of the oblique diameters of the pelvis.
The shoulders then descend rapidly and undergo internal rotation, with the bisacromial diameter occupying the anteroposterior plane.
Immediately following the shoulders, the head, which is normally sharply flexed on the thorax, enters the pelvis in one of the oblique diameters and then rotates to bring the posterior portion of the neck under the symphysis pubis.
The head is then born in flexion.
Infrequently, rotation renders the fetal back to lie posteriorly instead of anteriorly.
Such rotation is prevented if possible.
Although the head can be delivered by allowing the chin and face to pass beneath the symphysis, the slightest traction on the body may cause extension of the head.
With this, a longer diameter of the head must pass through the pelvis.
# Partial Breech Extraction.
With breech delivery, successively larger and less compressible parts are born.
Thus, spontaneous expulsion is the exception, and vaginal delivery typically requires skilled provider participation for the fetus to navigate the birth canal.
Noteworthy clinical pearls are provided by Yeomans (2017) in Cunningham and Gilstrap’s Operative Obstetrics, 3rd edition.
First, with all breech deliveries, unless the perineum is considerably lax, an episiotomy is made and is an important adjunct to delivery.
As discussed in Chapter 27 (p. 510), mediolateral episiotomy may be preferred for its lower associated risk of anal sphincter lacerations.
Ideally, the breech is allowed to deliver spontaneously to the umbilicus.
Delivery of the breech draws the umbilicus and attached cord into the pelvis.
Therefore, once the breech has passed beyond the vaginal introitus, the abdomen, thorax, arms, and head must be delivered promptly either spontaneously or assisted.
The posterior hip will deliver, usually from the 6 o’clock position, and often with sufficient pressure to evoke passage of thick meconium.
The anterior hip then delivers, followed by external rotation to a sacrum anterior position.
The mother is encouraged to continue to push as the fetus descends
until the legs are accessible.
The legs are sequentially delivered by splinting the femur with the operator’s fingers positioned parallel to the long axis of the femur.
This helps avoid femoral fracture.
Pressure is exerted upward and laterally to sweep each leg away from the midline .
Figure 28-3.
To deliver the left leg, two fingers of the provider’s left hand are placed beneath and parallel to the femur.
The thigh is then slightly abducted and pressure from the fingertips in the popliteal fossa should induce knee flexion and bring the foot within reach.
The foot is then grasped to gently deliver the entire leg outside the vagina.
A similar procedure is followed on the right.
Reproduced with permission from Yeomans ER: Vaginal breech delivery.
In Yeomans ER, Hoffman BL, Gilstrap LC III, et al [eds]: Cunningham and Gilstrap’s Operative Obstetrics, 3rd ed.
New York, NY: McGraw Hill; 2017.
Following delivery of the legs, the fetal bony pelvis is grasped with both hands.
The fingers should rest on the anterior superior iliac crests and the thumbs on the sacrum.
This minimizes the chance of fetal abdominal softtissue injury .
Maternal expulsive efforts are again used in conjunction with downward traction to affect delivery.
Figure 28-4.
To deliver the body, thumbs are placed over the sacrum, and each index finger wraps over the top of the corresponding fetal iliac crest.
Gentle downward traction is applied until the scapulas are clearly visible.
Reproduced with permission from Yeomans ER: Vaginal breech delivery.
In Yeomans ER, Hoffman BL, Gilstrap LC III, et al [eds]: Cunningham and Gilstrap’s Operative Obstetrics, 3rd ed.
New York, NY: McGraw Hill; 2017.
A cardinal rule in successful breech extraction is to employ steady, gentle, downward traction until the lower halves of the scapulas are delivered.
Subsequent delivery of the shoulders and arms is not attempted until one axilla becomes visible.
It makes little difference which shoulder is delivered first, and two methods are suitable for their delivery.
In the first method, with the scapulas visible, the trunk is rotated either clockwise or counterclockwise to bring the anterior shoulder and arm into view .
During delivery of the arm, fingers and hand are aligned parallel to the humerus and act as a splint.
Perpendicular force risks humeral fracture.
The body of the fetus is then rotated 180 degrees in the reverse direction to bring the other shoulder and arm into position for delivery.
Figure 28-5.
A. After delivery of the first arm, 180-degree rotation of the fetal body brings the sacrum to a right sacrum transverse (RST) position.
B. Fingers of the provider’s hand extended over the right shoulder and parallel to the humerus.
These sweep the arm downward across the chest and out.
Reproduced with permission from Yeomans ER: Vaginal breech delivery.
In Yeomans ER, Hoffman BL, Gilstrap LC III, et al [eds]: Cunningham and Gilstrap’s Operative Obstetrics, 3rd ed.
New York, NY: McGraw Hill; 2017.
The second method is employed if trunk rotation is unsuccessful.
With this maneuver, the posterior shoulder is delivered first.
For this, the feet are grasped in one hand and drawn upward over the inner thigh of the mother .
The operator’s hand enters over the fetal shoulder, fingers are aligned parallel to the long axis of the fetal humerus, and the fetal arm is swept upward.
The posterior shoulder slides out over the perineal margin and is usually followed by the arm and hand.
Then, by depressing the body of the fetus, the anterior shoulder emerges beneath the pubic arch, and the arm and hand usually follow spontaneously.
After both shoulders are delivered, the back of the fetus tends to rotate spontaneously to the symphysis.
Delivery of the head may then be accomplished.
Figure 28-6.
Infrequently, the posterior arm must be delivered first.
For this, the lower half of the fetal body is raised up and over the maternal groin.
The provider’s fingers are inserted under the posterior shoulder and aligned with the humerus.
Reproduced with permission from Yeomans
ER: Vaginal breech delivery.
In Yeomans ER, Hoffman BL, Gilstrap LC III, et al [eds]: Cunningham and Gilstrap’s Operative Obstetrics, 3rd ed.
New York, NY: McGraw Hill; 2017.
Nuchal Arm During delivery, one or both fetal arms occasionally may lie across the back of the neck and become trapped at the pelvic inlet.
With such a nuchal arm, delivery is more difficult and can be aided by rotating the fetus through a half circle in such a direction that the friction exerted by the birth canal will draw the elbow toward the face .
With a right nuchal arm, the body should be rotated counterclockwise, which rotates the fetal back toward the maternal right.
With a left nuchal arm, the rotation is clockwise, which rotates the fetal back toward the maternal left.
If rotation fails to free the nuchal arm, it may be necessary to push the fetus upward to a roomier part of the pelvis.
If the rotation is still unsuccessful, still in this roomier part of the pelvic, the nuchal arm can be extracted.
For this, the operator’s hand enters over the fetal shoulder, and fingers are aligned parallel to the long axis of the fetal humerus.
Downward pressure flexes the elbow, and the fetal arm is then swept forward and down the ventral body surface for delivery.
In this event, fracture of the humerus or clavicle is common.
Figure 28-7.
Reduction of a right nuchal arm is accomplished by rotating the fetal body 180 degrees counterclockwise, which directs the fetal back to the maternal right.
Friction exerted by the birth canal will draw the elbow toward the face.
Delivery of the Aftercoming Head The head of the fetus is normally extracted with one of the three maneuvers.
With any of these, hyperextension of the fetal neck is avoided.
First, with the Mauriceau maneuver, the index and middle finger of one hand are applied over the maxilla, to flex the head, while the fetal body rests on the palm of the same hand and forearm .
Fetal legs straddle the forearm.
Two fingers of the other hand hook over and grasp the shoulders.
Downward traction is concurrently applied until the suboccipital region appears under the symphysis.
Gentle suprapubic pressure simultaneously applied by an assistant helps keep the head flexed.
The body is slightly elevated toward the maternal abdomen, and the mouth, nose, brow, and eventually the occiput emerge successively over the perineum.
With this maneuver, the provider uses both hands simultaneously to exert continuous downward gentle traction while balancing forces between the fetal neck and maxilla to avoid neck hyperextension.
Figure 28-8.
A. Delivery of the aftercoming head using the Mauriceau maneuver.
Note that as the fetal head is being delivered, flexion of the head is maintained by suprapubic pressure provided by an assistant.
B. Pressure on the maxilla is applied simultaneously by the operator as upward and outward traction is exerted.
Second, specialized forceps can be used to deliver the aftercoming head.
Piper forceps, shown in Figure 28-9, or Laufe-Piper forceps may be applied electively or when the Mauriceau maneuver cannot be accomplished easily.
The blades of the forceps are not applied to the aftercoming head until it has been brought into the pelvis by gentle traction, combined with suprapubic pressure, and is engaged.
Suspension of the body of the fetus in a towel effectively holds the fetus up and helps keep the arms and cord out of the way as the forceps blades are applied.
Figure 28-9.
Piper forceps for delivery of the aftercoming head.
Because the forceps blades are directed upward from the level of the perineum, some choose to apply them from a one-knee kneeling position.
Piper forceps have a downward arch in the shank to accommodate the fetal body and lack a pelvic curve.
This shape permits direct application of the cephalic curve of the blade along the length of the maternal vagina and fetal parietal bone.
The blade to be placed on the maternal left is held in the provider’s left hand.
The right hand slides between the fetal head and left maternal vaginal sidewall to guide the blade inward
and around the parietal bone.
The opposite blade mirrors this application.
Once in place, the blades are articulated, and the fetal body rests across the shanks.
The head is delivered by pulling gently outward and slightly raising the handle simultaneously.
This rolls the face over the perineum, while the occiput remains beneath the symphysis until after the brow delivers.
Ideally, the head and body move in unison to minimize neck extension.
Last, in some cases, the back of the fetus fails to rotate to the symphysis.
The fetus still may be delivered using the modified Prague maneuver.
With this, two fingers of one hand grasp the shoulders of the back-down fetus from below while the other hand draws the feet up and over the maternal abdomen .
Figure 28-10.
Delivery of the aftercoming head using the modified Prague maneuver necessitated by failure of the fetal trunk to rotate anteriorly.
Head Entrapment Either an incompletely dilated cervix or cephalopelvic disproportion can entrap the head.
At this point, a true emergency exists because significant cord compression must be assumed.
First, an incompletely dilated cervix can constrict around the neck, especially with a small preterm fetus.
With gentle traction on the fetal body, the cervix at times may be manually slipped over the occiput.
If unsuccessful, Dührssen incisions may be needed .
General anesthesia with halogenated agents is another option to aid lower uterine segment relaxation.
As an extreme measure, replacement of the fetus higher into the vagina and uterus, followed by cesarean delivery, can rescue an entrapped breech fetus.
This Zavanelli maneuver is classically performed to relieve intractable shoulder dystocia .
However, case reports have also described its use for an entrapped aftercoming head (Sandberg, 1999; Steyn, 1994).
Figure 28-11.
Dührssen incision being cut at 2 o’clock, which is followed by a second incision if needed at 10 o’clock.
Infrequently, an additional incision is required at 6 o’clock.
The incisions are so placed as to minimize bleeding from the laterally located cervical branches of the uterine artery.
After delivery, the incisions are repaired as described in Chapter 42 (p. 740).
Second, in cases with cephalopelvic disproportion and arrest of aftercoming head, the Zavanelli maneuver or symphysiotomy are options (Sunday-Adeoye, 2004; Wery, 2013).
These are described in Chapter 27 (p. 504).
# Total Breech Extraction.
Frank Breech During complete extraction of a frank breech, moderate traction is exerted by a finger in each groin and aided by a generous episiotomy.
Once the breech is pulled through the introitus, the steps just described for partial breech extraction are completed.
Rarely during vaginal delivery, a frank breech will require decomposition inside the uterine cavity.
Attributed to Pinard (1889), this procedure converts a frank breech into a footling breech.
It is accomplished more readily if the membranes have ruptured only recently.
It becomes extremely difficult if amnionic fluid is scant and the uterus is tightly contracted around the fetus.
Pharmacological relaxation by general anesthesia or intravenous magnesium sulfate, nitroglycerin, or a betamimetic agent may be required.
To begin, two fingers are carried up along one leg to externally rotate the hip by pressing on the medial side of the thigh parallel to the femur.
Simultaneously, pressure in the popliteal fossa should prompt spontaneous knee flexion which brings the corresponding foot into contact with the back of the provider’s hand.
The fetal foot then may be grasped and brought down.
Delivery is then accomplished as for incomplete breech, described next.
Incomplete or Complete Breech If rapid labor progress prohibits cesarean delivery, total extraction of an incomplete or complete breech may be required.
A hand is introduced through the vagina, and both fetal feet are grasped.
The ankles are held with the middle finger lying between them.
With gentle traction, the feet are brought through the introitus .
As the legs begin to emerge through the vulva,
downward gentle traction is continued.
As the legs emerge, successively higher portions are grasped.
When the breech appears at the vaginal outlet, gentle traction is applied until the hips are delivered.
The thumbs are then placed over the sacrum and the fingers over the iliac crests.
Breech extraction is then completed, as described for partial breech extraction.
Figure 28-12.
Complete breech extraction begins with traction on the feet and ankles.
If only one foot can be grasped, it can be brought down into the vagina and held with the appropriate hand, right hand for right foot and left hand for left foot .
With the first foot secure, the opposite hand is introduced, passed upward along the leg, and guided to locate the other foot.
If the remaining hip is extended, the second foot is usually easily grasped and brought down.
If the hip is flexed and knee extended, a finger is hooked into that groin, and traction will bring the lower half of the fetus down until the leg can be reached.
For cesarean delivery, these same total breech extraction maneuvers can be used.
These steps can aid delivery of a frank, complete, or incomplete breech through the hysterotomy incision.
External Cephalic Version.
With version, fetal presentation is altered by physically substituting one pole of a longitudinal presentation for the other, or converting an oblique or transverse lie into a longitudinal presentation.
Manipulations performed through the abdominal wall that yield a cephalic presentation are termed external cephalic version.
Manipulations accomplished inside the uterine cavity that yield a breech presentation are designated internal podalic version.
This latter procedure is reserved for delivery of a second twin and described in Chapter 48 (p. 856).
# Indications.
External cephalic version (ECV) reduces the rate of noncephalic presentation at birth, and its success rate is 50 to 60 percent (Hofmeyr, 2015b; Melo, 2019).
For women with a transverse lie, the overall success rate is significantly higher.
In general, ECV is attempted before labor in a woman who has reached 370/7 weeks’ gestation (American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists, 2020; Impey, 2017a).
This threshold aims to balance risks of fetal immaturity and the greater amnionic fluid volume seen in early-term pregnancies, which aids turning.
In support of this, one systematic review found that ECV done before 370/7 weeks raised ECV success rates but did not lower the ultimate cesarean delivery rate and increased the risk of latepreterm birth .
Before this time, breech presentation also still has a high likelihood of correcting spontaneously.
And, if ECV is performed too early, time may allow a reversion back to breech .
Last, if attempts at version cause a need for immediate delivery, complications of iatrogenic early-term delivery generally are not severe.
Absolute contraindications to ECV are few.
It is contraindicated if vaginal delivery is not an option, such as with placenta previa.
Relative contraindications are early labor, oligohydramnios or ruptured membranes, known nuchal cord, structural uterine abnormalities, fetal-growth restriction, multifetal gestation, and prior abruption or its risk factors .
Little data guide the decision for ECV for women with a prior cesarean delivery.
In one pooled series of small studies that contained more than 100 attempts, no uterine ruptures were reported .
At Parkland Hospital, we do not attempt ECV in these women.
Several factors can improve the chances of an ECV attempt.
These are multiparity, unengaged presenting part, nonanterior placenta, nonobese patient, and abundant amnionic fluid (Lauterbach, 2021; Kok, 2008, 2009).
To augment the last parameter, neither a preprocedural 2-L intravenous fluid bolus nor amnioinfusion raised ECV success rates (Burgos, 2014; Diguisto, 2018).
Dedicated breech teams may increase these rates (Hickland, 2018; Thissen, 2019).
# Complications.
Patient counseling includes a discussion regarding small but real risks for placental abruption, preterm labor, and fetal compromise.
Bradycardia is common during or following ECV, but emergent cesarean rates are ≤0.5 percent.
Uterine rupture, fetomaternal hemorrhage, alloimmunization, amnionic fluid embolism, and maternal or fetal deaths are rare (Grootscholten, 2008; Rodgers, 2017).
Overall, compared with expectant management, perinatal morbidity and mortality rates are not greater with ECV (Krueger, 2018; Son, 2018).
Even after successful ECV, several reports suggest that the cesarean delivery rate does not completely revert to the baseline for vertex presentations.
Specifically, dystocia, malpresentation, and nonreassuring fetal heart patterns may be more common in these fetuses who have undergone successful ECV (Chan, 2004; de Hundt, 2014; Vézina, 2004).
# Technique.
ECV should be carried out in an area that has ready access to a facility equipped to perform emergency cesarean delivery.
Because of the risk for surgical intervention, intravenous access is obtained.
Patients also abstain from eating for 6 hours, but clear liquids can be consumed up to 2 hours prior.
Sonographic examination is performed to confirm nonvertex presentation, document amnionic fluid volume adequacy, exclude obvious fetal anomalies if not done previously, and identify placental location and fetal spine orientation.
Preprocedural external monitoring is performed to document fetal heart rate reactivity.
Anti-D immune globulin is given to Rh D–negative women.
Tocolysis and regional analgesia may be elected, and rationale for these is provided in subsequent sections.
The woman is placed in left lateral tilt to aid uteroplacental perfusion, and Trendelenburg positioning helps during elevation of the breech.
During the procedure, we prefer to monitor fetal heart motion sonographically.
An abundant abdominal coating of ultrasound gel permits this and also minimizes painful skin friction .
A forward roll of the fetus usually is attempted first.
One or two providers may participate, and one hand grasps the head.
The fetal buttocks are then elevated from the maternal pelvis and displaced laterally .
These are then gently guided toward the fundus, while the head is simultaneously directed toward the pelvis.
If the forward roll is unsuccessful, a backward flip is attempted.
ECV attempts are discontinued for excessive discomfort, for persistently abnormal fetal heart rate, or after multiple failed attempts.
Failure is not always absolute.
Ben-Meir and colleagues (2007) reported a spontaneous version rate of 7 percent among 226 failed versions—2 percent among nulliparas and 13 percent among multiparas.
Figure 28-13.
External cephalic version.
With an attempted forward roll, clockwise pressure is exerted against the fetal poles.
If ECV is successful, a nonstress test is repeated until a normal test result is obtained.
A transient abnormal fetal heart rate tracing during or after ECV complicates 6 to 9 percent of cases.
This should prompt a traditional resuscitative response with intravenous fluids, oxygen, and lateral tilt.
Rates of abnormal tracings prompting immediate cesarean delivery range from only 0.2 to 0.4 percent (Collaris, 2004; Grootscholten, 2008).
Once resolved, Kuppens and coworkers (2017) found that a transient abnormal tracing did not predict later fetal distress in subsequent labor.
If ECV is completed before 39 weeks’ gestation, awaiting spontaneous labor and fetal maturity is preferred.
In some studies, immediate labor induction is linked to higher cesarean delivery rates (Burgos, 2015; Kuppens, 2013).
Tocolysis By relaxing the uterus prior to an ECV attempt, tocolysis raises success rates.
Most data support the use of the betamimetics terbutaline and ritodrine for this .
In one such trial, Fernandez and coworkers (1996) reported that the success rate with subcutaneous terbutaline—52 percent— was significantly higher than without—27 percent.
Our policy at Parkland Hospital is to administer 250 μg of terbutaline subcutaneously to most women before attempted ECV.
When maternal tachycardia—a known side effect of terbutaline—is noted, the attempt is
begun.
Terbutaline readily crosses the placenta, and mild elevation of fetal heart rate baseline also is possible (Ingemarsson, 1981; Roth, 1990).
Data are limited and in some cases are nonsupportive for other agents that include calcium-channel blockers, such as nifedipine; nitric oxide donors, such as nitroglycerin; the oxytocin-receptor antagonist atosiban; and another betamimetic salbutamol (Burgos, 2010; Cluver, 2015; Hilton, 2009; Levin, 2019; Vani, 2009; Wilcox, 2011).
Conduction Analgesia Epidural analgesia coupled with tocolysis has been reported to raise ECV success rates compared with tocolysis alone (Goetzinger, 2011; MagroMalosso, 2016).
Moreover, rates of complications that include fetal heart rate aberrations, emergency cesarean delivery, or placental abruption are not greater with regional analgesia.
In trials, spinal and epidural have both shown success and are reasonable options (Khaw, 2015; Weiniger, 2010).
Although uncommon, risks specific to regional analgesia, such as spinal headache, are possible.
Currently, the superior technique and best drugs to administer are unclear.
In contrast, from limited data, intravenous sedation or nitrous oxide does not appear to improve ECV success (Burgos, 2016; Dochez, 2019; Khaw, 2015; Straube, 2021).
# Moxibustion.
This is a traditional Chinese medicine technique that burns a cigarette-shaped stick of ground Artemisia vulgaris—which is also known as mugwort or in Japanese as moxa.
At the BL 67 acupuncture point, the stick is directly placed against the skin or indirectly heats an acupuncture needle at the site to increase fetal movement and promote spontaneous breech version .
It is performed usually between 33 and 36 weeks’ gestation to permit a trial of ECV if not successful.
Results from randomized controlled studies are conflicting (Bue, 2016; Coulon, 2014; Coyle, 2012; Sananes, 2016; Vas, 2013).